A tornado is 100 mph. A hurricane is 150. This is something else!
500 MPH Storm is a action, science fiction, tv
movie film directed by Daniel Lusko.
When an energy experiment goes haywire, a rash of
massive hurricanes rips across North America.
A high school science teacher must get his family to safety before the hurricanes
merge, creating a "hypercane" with the power to wipe the US off the map.
Nathan Sims, played by Casper Van Dien.
Mona Sims, played by Sarah Lieving.
Simon Caprisi, played by Michael Beach.
Captain Wright, played by Keith Meriweather.
Corporal Gentile, played by Alex Knight.
Tech Oxenberg, played by Dale O´Malley.
The 2013 El Reno tornado was an extremely large, powerful, and erratic tornado that occurred and hit
a rural part of Central Oklahoma during the early evening of Friday, May 31, 2013.
This rain-wrapped, multiple-vortex tornado was the widest
tornado ever recorded, peaking at 2.6 miles across.
It was part of a larger weather system that produced
dozens of tornadoes over the preceding days.
The tornado initially formed at 6:03 p.m.
CDT (23:03 UTC) about 8.3 miles (13.4 km) west-southwest of El Reno, rapidly growing in
size and becoming more violent as it tracked through central Canadian County.
Remaining over mostly open terrain, the tornado did not impact many structures; however, measurements from
mobile weather radars revealed extreme winds in excess of 313 mph (504 km/h) within sub-vortices.
These are among the highest observed wind speeds on Earth, just slightly lower
than the wind speeds of the 1999 Bridge Creek–Moore tornado.
As it crossed U.S.
81, it had grown to a record-breaking width of 2.6 miles (4.2
km), beating the previous width record set in 2004.
Turning northeastward, the tornado soon weakened.
Upon crossing Interstate 40, the tornado dissipated around 6:43 p.m.
CDT (23:43 UTC), after tracking for 16.2 miles (26.1 km).
It avoided affecting more densely populated areas near and
within the Oklahoma City metropolitan area.
The tornado killed four storm chasers (three professional and one
amateur), the first known deaths in the history of storm chasing.
Although the tornado remained over mostly open terrain, dozens of storm chasers
unaware of its immense size and erratic movement were caught off-guard.
81, TWISTEX scientist and engineer Tim Samaras, along with his son Paul
and research partner Carl Young, died in the tornado.
Paul Samaras and Young were ejected from their Chevrolet Cobalt by the storm's
sub-vortex, while Tim was still buckled in the passenger's seat.
Local resident Richard Henderson, who decided to follow
the storm, lost his life in that same area.
He snapped a picture of the tornado from his
cellular phone before it struck him.
Other chasers, including Mike Bettes of The Weather Channel and Reed
Timmer, either were injured or had their vehicles damaged.
A Doppler on Wheels-based analysis of how the tornado impacted these teams
revealed that they were hit by an intense internal sub-vortex.
Overall, the tornado was responsible for eight fatalities and 151 injuries.
Due to the ferocity and sheer size, as well as its irregular movement and the deaths linked with
this tornado, it has become one of the most studied and infamous tornadoes ever.
The National Weather Service referred to the tornado as "the most dangerous tornado in storm observing history."
Alongside rush hour traffic, thousands of
residents in Oklahoma City attempted to outrun the storm by taking to the roads in an attempt to drive out of the tornado's projected path.
By attempting to escape the storm by vehicle, in direct contrast to the recommended plan of action, residents put themselves at great risk from
the storm; had the tornado maintained itself and passed over the congested freeways, more than 500 lives could have been lost.
The film explores themes of experiment, tornado,
hurricane, hot air balloon, scientist.
The tone is emotional and thought_provoking and intense.